<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bassam Saeed</title>
    <link>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bassam Saeed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up LXC with Networking</title>
      <link>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/lxc-container-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/lxc-container-networking/</guid>
      <description>From my understanding Ubuntu will setup a bridge by default when you install lxc. Or perhaps when you first create a container. I&amp;rsquo;m not certain. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the case in a lot of other distributions however.
In this guide we&amp;rsquo;ll setup a network bridge. The bridge with be setup on the host system to aggregate the internal container networks with the outer network. In this way the host system will become a bridge from the router to the containers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How-To: Encrypted Btrfs install on Arch Linux</title>
      <link>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/encrypted-btrfs-archlinux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/encrypted-btrfs-archlinux/</guid>
      <description>Setting up a Btrfs install while juggling encyption, UEFI, and swap can be tricky so I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to put down my method here. Btrfs is damn flexible and can do a lot of things from replacing the MBR/GPT schemes to RAID and then some. Unfortunately it does have some limitations. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have built-in encyption, doesn&amp;rsquo;t support swap files and -not its fault- can&amp;rsquo;t use UEFI to boot. Encryption can be solved using dm-crypt and the other issues by having their own partitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting up with Jekyll and Github</title>
      <link>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/starting-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 16:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bassamsaeed.ca/blog/starting-up/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to actually create a website in order to document my learning as well as interesting information or methodology I stumble across. Essentially a way for me to keep track of certain details that I might need to refer back to. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;ll be helpful for others too.
Up to this point I&amp;rsquo;ve used a self-hosted wiki to manage this type of information (as well as cooking recipes). This blog is meant to be essentially an extension of that with more detail and my thought process and reasoning behind the decisions I make.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>